(Adapted from the Jinjiang Literature City novel, "Dazzling")
(Adaptado de la novela "Deslumbrante" de la Ciudad Literaria de Jinjiang)
(Original work by Shi Jiu Yuan)
(Obra original de Shi Jiu Yuan)
(Episode 15)
(Episodio 15)
Zhu Feng.
Zhu Feng.
Did you hear?
¿Lo oíste?
Your ex-wife and Xing Wu's mom
Tu exesposa y madre de Xing Wu
fought and ended up at the police station.
Se pelearon y terminaron en la comisaría.
What? The police station?
¿Qué? ¿La comisaría?
How is that possible? Don't listen to those rumors.
¿Cómo es posible? No hagas caso a esos rumores.
Ask around if you don't believe me.
Pregunta a tu alrededor si no me crees.
Let me tell you, it wasn't easy for you
Déjame decirte que no fue fácil para ti.
to get a top student like Qing Ye.
para conseguir una estudiante sobresaliente como Qing Ye.
You mustn't let
No debes dejar
your family matters affect her.
Tus asuntos familiares le afectan.
Don't let her end up like...
No dejes que termine así...
Xing Wu.
Xing Wu.
(Xuandao Show Hair Salon)
(Salón de belleza Xuandao Show)
Why isn't this light box working?
¿Por qué no funciona esta caja de luz?
It was fine yesterday.
Ayer estuvo bien.
When bad luck strikes,
Cuando la mala suerte golpea,
everything goes wrong.
Todo sale mal.
Just my luck!
¡Qué mala suerte la mía!
(Xuandao Show Hair Salon)
(Salón de belleza Xuandao Show)
What's going on here?
¿Qué está pasando aquí?
Is there a power outage?
¿Hay un corte de luz?
It's probably a loose connection.
Probablemente sea una conexión floja.
I'll fix it in a bit.
Lo arreglaré en un rato.
How is Grandma doing?
¿Cómo está la abuela?
I've admitted her to the hospital.
La he ingresado en el hospital.
Shu Han is watching over her now.
Shu Han la está cuidando ahora.
- Don't worry. - Fang Fang.
- No te preocupes. - Fang Fang.
She's fine.
Ella está bien.
You're back.
Has vuelto.
What exactly happened?
¿Qué fue exactamente lo que pasó?
Come on, let's talk inside Love Mahjong.
Vamos, hablemos dentro de Love Mahjong.
Let's go. We'll talk inside Love Mahjong.
Vamos. Hablaremos dentro de Love Mahjong.
- Are you okay? - What could be wrong with me?
- ¿Estás bien? - ¿Qué me puede pasar?
So Shu Han is taking care of Grandma?
¿Así que Shu Han está cuidando a la abuela?
Canine and Shu Han
Canino y Shu Han
will take turns tonight.
Esta noche nos turnaremos.
I'll bring a few things over tomorrow.
Mañana llevaré algunas cosas.
The surgery will be expensive, right?
La cirugía será cara, ¿verdad?
Is there anything I can do to help?
¿Hay algo que pueda hacer para ayudar?
Don't you worry about that.
No te preocupes por eso.
You're a student.
Eres estudiante.
Just focus on your studies.
Concéntrate en tus estudios.
(Xuandao Show Hair Salon)
(Salón de belleza Xuandao Show)
Why are you back?
¿Por qué has vuelto?
Grandma is more important.
La abuela es más importante.
I just came by to see
Solo vine a ver
if there's anything I can help with.
Si hay algo en lo que pueda ayudar.
It's fine. Don't worry about it.
Está bien. No te preocupes.
Can you stop trying to carry
¿Puedes dejar de intentar cargar?
everything on your own?
¿Todo por tu cuenta?
I may seem heartless,
Puede que parezca insensible,
but that's only because
pero eso es solo porque
I'm trying to give myself a way out.
Estoy tratando de encontrar una salida.
For Grandma's surgery,
Para la cirugía de la abuela,
we might need over 10,000 yuan.
Podríamos necesitar más de 10.000 yuanes.
I know.
Lo sé.
I'll find a way.
Encontraré la manera.
I'll find a way too.
Yo también encontraré la manera.
- Yu Fen. - Fang Fang.
-Yu Fen. - Colmillo Colmillo.
Why did you leave so suddenly?
¿Por qué te fuiste tan de repente?
We know you're in a tough spot.
Sabemos que estás pasando por una situación difícil.
Don't be shy about asking us for money.
No tengas reparo en pedirnos dinero.
When you came to the shop just now,
Cuando llegaste a la tienda hace un momento,
everyone could tell.
Todo el mundo podía darse cuenta.
Actually,
De hecho,
I...
I...
Xi Xi and I discussed it.
Xi Xi y yo lo hablamos.
We can scrape together 6,000 yuan for you.
Podemos reunir 6.000 yuanes para usted.
As for the rest, we neighbors
En cuanto al resto, nosotros los vecinos
will help you think of something.
te ayudará a pensar en algo.
Don't feel pressured.
No te sientas presionado.
My best trait is my optimism.
Mi mejor cualidad es mi optimismo.
Hello, Da Hei.
Hola, entonces.
I... need a favor.
Yo... necesito un favor.
Well, here's the thing.
Bueno, aquí está la cuestión.
Something happened to my grandma.
Algo le pasó a mi abuela.
She's in the hospital.
Ella está en el hospital.
I'm a bit short on cash.
Ando un poco corto de dinero.
Can you lend me
¿Me puedes prestar?
5,000 yuan for now?
¿5.000 yuanes por ahora?
If not, 3,000,
Si no, 3.000,
or even 2,000 is fine.
o incluso 2.000 está bien.
Okay, okay. No problem.
Vale, vale. No hay problema.
Great.
Excelente.
Thanks a lot.
Muchas gracias.
I really appreciate it.
Lo agradezco mucho.
Qing Ye,
Qing Ye,
can you tutor me in English?
¿Puedes darme clases particulares de inglés?
I'll pay you.
Te pagaré.
Hello, Qing Ye.
Hola Qingye.
Hello,
Hola,
about the English tutoring you mentioned
sobre las clases particulares de inglés que mencionaste
at 300 per lesson,
a 300 por lección,
does the offer still stand?
¿Sigue en pie la oferta?
Of course.
Por supuesto.
Okay, I'll do it.
De acuerdo, lo haré.
But I have conditions.
Pero tengo condiciones.
Name them.
Nómbralos.
Pay a deposit up front.
Pague un depósito por adelantado.
Minimum booking of 10 lessons.
Reserva mínima de 10 clases.
Book 10, get 1 free.
Reserva 10 y llévate 1 gratis.
I decide the time and place.
Yo decido la hora y el lugar.
No problem.
Ningún problema.
I'll take 20 lessons to start.
Tomaré 20 lecciones para empezar.
Okay.
Bueno.
(6,000 yuan sent. Please accept.)
(Se han enviado 6.000 yuanes. Por favor, acepte.)
Qing Ye, good morning.
Qing Ye, buenos días.
- Shu Han. - Get in.
- Shu Han. - Entra.
Wait, I thought the tutoring was in the evening.
Espera, creía que las clases particulares eran por la tarde.
Why are you here so early in the morning?
¿Por qué estás aquí tan temprano por la mañana?
Shu Han said it's on her way.
Shu Han dijo que ya viene en camino.
She's giving us a ride to school today.
Hoy nos lleva al colegio en coche.
I have to pick you up anyway.
De todas formas tengo que ir a recogerte.
I'll drop them off at school,
Los llevaré a la escuela,
then head to the county town.
Luego diríjase a la capital del condado.
Let's go.
Vamos.
I sent you the new contract.
Te envié el nuevo contrato.
It's been revised according to your requirements.
Se ha revisado de acuerdo con sus requisitos.
When you have a moment, take a good look at it.
Cuando tengas un momento, obsérvalo con atención.
Mr. Ye is being very sincere this time.
El señor Ye está siendo muy sincero esta vez.
He wants to sign you on
Él quiere contratarte
as a full-time employee for three years.
como empleada a tiempo completo durante tres años.
Give it some serious thought.
Piénsalo seriamente.
I've read the contract. It looks fine.
He leído el contrato. Parece estar bien.
Print it out and get the process started.
Imprímelo y comienza el proceso.
Okay.
Bueno.
Qing Ye, I have a contract too.
Qing Ye, yo también tengo un contrato.
I thought about it last night.
Lo pensé anoche.
I think our relationship
Creo que nuestra relación
should be more formal.
debería ser más formal.
What relationship?
¿Qué relación?
A teacher-student relationship.
Una relación profesor-alumno.
This contract is proof of that.
Este contrato es prueba de ello.
For these 20 lessons,
Para estas 20 lecciones,
you can't skip a single one.
No puedes saltarte ni uno solo.
Not even the two free ones.
Ni siquiera los dos gratuitos.
And no refunds allowed.
Y no se admiten devoluciones.
You're tutoring him?
¿Le estás dando clases particulares?
Since when?
¿Desde cuándo?
We agreed last night.
Llegamos a un acuerdo anoche.
Starting today.
A partir de hoy.
Xing Wu, look.
Xing Wu, mira.
You and Shu Han
Tú y Shu Han
both work for my dad.
Ambos trabajan para mi padre.
I'm a VVVIP at Xuandao,
Soy un VVVIP en Xuandao,
and now Qing Ye is my teacher.
Y ahora Qing Ye es mi profesor.
I think the Xuandao family and I
Creo que la familia Xuandao y yo
are really meant to be.
Realmente están destinados a estar juntos.
Get in the car.
Sube al coche.
Coming.
Próximo.
Ye Ying Jian, hurry up!
¡Ye Yingjian, date prisa!
Coming! Give me a second.
¡Ya voy! Dame un segundo.
Qing Ye, remember to sign the contract!
Qing Ye, ¡recuerda firmar el contrato!
Qing Ye.
Qingye.
Could you not sign
¿No podrías firmar?
that contract from Ye Ying Jian?
¿Ese contrato de Ye Ying Jian?
Then could you not sign
Entonces, ¿no podrías firmar?
that contract from Shu Han?
¿Ese contrato de Shu Han?
Your job is to study hard here,
Tu trabajo aquí es estudiar mucho,
and leave this place after the college entrance exam.
y abandonar este lugar después del examen de ingreso a la universidad.
Tutoring is just a side thing.
Dar clases particulares es solo una actividad secundaria.
It won't affect my studies.
No afectará a mis estudios.
I know you mean well,
Sé que tienes buenas intenciones,
- and want to help Grandma. - Exactly.
- y quiero ayudar a la abuela. - Exacto.
You know
Sabes
I can't just stand by and do nothing.
No puedo quedarme de brazos cruzados sin hacer nada.
But earning a few thousand yuan can't solve our family's problems.
Pero ganar unos miles de yuanes no puede solucionar los problemas de nuestra familia.
In one more week,
En una semana más,
I'll lose my student status.
Perderé mi condición de estudiante.
Tell Zhu Feng to just cancel it.
Dile a Zhu Feng que simplemente lo cancele.
You really don't plan to return to school?
¿De verdad no piensas volver a la escuela?
No.
No.
(Notice of Temporary Closure for Corrective Action)
(Aviso de cierre temporal para medidas correctivas)
Liu Nian.
Liu Nian.
Ms. Fang.
Señora Fang.
This is an IOU.
Esto es un pagaré.
Take it.
Tómalo.
I'll pay back every cent I owe you.
Te devolveré hasta el último centavo que te debo.
During this time, find your friends,
Durante este tiempo, encuentra a tus amigos,
and do some odd jobs.
y hacer algunos trabajos ocasionales.
When we're ready to reopen,
Cuando estemos listos para reabrir,
I'll let you know.
Te avisaré.
Ms. Fang, I haven't worked these past few days.
Señora Fang, no he trabajado estos últimos días.
Shouldn't you deduct that from my pay?
¿No deberías descontarlo de mi sueldo?
I won't deduct a single cent.
No voy a descontar ni un solo centavo.
Just take it.
Tómalo.
I have the money.
Tengo el dinero.
So, Ms. Fang,
Entonces, Sra. Fang,
when can we reopen?
¿Cuándo podremos reabrir?
I believe
Yo creo
it will be very soon.
Será muy pronto.
Who is it?
¿Quién es?
Coming!
¡Próximo!
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
I... I'm here to see you.
Yo... estoy aquí para verte.
Open the door and let me in.
Abre la puerta y déjame entrar.
Hey, Xiao Lian.
Hola, Xiao Lian.
Xiao Lian, I'm really here to apologize,
Xiao Lian, realmente estoy aquí para disculparme,
and patch things up with you.
y arreglar las cosas contigo.
Well... Xiao Lian, I'll head out then.
Bueno... Xiao Lian, me marcho entonces.
I'll leave the food I bought you
Te dejaré la comida que te compré.
at the door.
en la puerta.
Remember to eat it.
Recuerda comértelo.
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
Xiao Lian!
¡Xiao Lian!
Xiao Lian. Xiao...
Xiaolian. Xiao...
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
This.
Este.
I spent money on all this.
Gasté dinero en todo esto.
Hand out the test papers to everyone.
Reparte los exámenes a todos.
Mr. Zhu.
Sr. Zhu
Could you sign this for me?
¿Podrías firmarme esto?
- A leave request? - Yes.
- ¿Una solicitud de permiso? - Sí.
I'd like to be excused
Quisiera que me disculparan.
from evening self-study at school this week.
de estudio autodidacta vespertino en la escuela esta semana.
My grandma is in the hospital.
Mi abuela está en el hospital.
I need to be there with her.
Necesito estar allí con ella.
But I promise I won't fall behind in my studies.
Pero prometo que no me quedaré atrás en mis estudios.
Alright.
Está bien.
Thank you, Teacher.
Gracias, profesor.
Oh, Qing Ye.
Ah, Qingye.
About that thing I mentioned last time,
Sobre aquello que mencioné la última vez,
how did your talk with Xing Wu go?
¿Cómo te fue en tu conversación con Xing Wu?
Grandma needs looking after,
La abuela necesita que la cuiden,
Xuandao has some issues to sort out,
Xuandao tiene algunos problemas que resolver,
and things at home are a mess.
y en casa hay un desastre.
I understand.
Entiendo.
Alright, you can go.
De acuerdo, puedes irte.
(Name: Xing Wu)
(Nombre: Xing Wu)
Wu Zi.
Wu Zi.
Take a break.
Hacer una pausa.
I can sleep now.
Ya puedo dormir.
Go to sleep.
Ve a dormir.
Your student status has been canceled.
Tu condición de estudiante ha sido cancelada.
Don't you think it's a pity?
¿No te parece una lástima?
(Don't you think it's a pity?)
(¿No te parece una lástima?)
(It's not a pity at all.)
(No es ninguna lástima).
(Letter of Intent for Cooperation with Electronics Street)
(Carta de intención de cooperación con Electronics Street)
(Xing Wu)
(Xing Wu)
Qing Ye.
Qingye.
Why are you leaving?
¿Por qué te vas?
Aren't you staying for evening self-study?
¿No te quedas para estudiar por tu cuenta esta noche?
I've taken leave.
Me he tomado un permiso.
Leave?
¿Dejar?
Did something happen?
¿Ha pasado algo?
Not really.
No precisamente.
You suddenly want to tutor me.
De repente quieres darme clases particulares.
Is it because my grades are good,
¿Es porque mis notas son buenas?
and you want to help me improve?
¿Y quieres ayudarme a mejorar?
That way, we can get into a good university together.
De esa forma, podremos entrar juntos en una buena universidad.
You still look unhappy.
Sigues pareciendo infeliz.
Are you short on money?
¿Te falta dinero?
Is there anything that money can't solve?
¿Hay algo que el dinero no pueda solucionar?
I used to think like you.
Yo solía pensar como tú.
But my recent experiences
Pero mis experiencias recientes
have taught me
me han enseñado
that some problems
que algunos problemas
cannot be solved with any amount of money.
No se puede solucionar con ninguna cantidad de dinero.
Is there really anything
¿Hay realmente algo?
that money can't solve?
¿Eso no lo puede solucionar el dinero?
I used to be very confused.
Antes estaba muy confundido.
Why couldn't he choose
¿Por qué no pudo elegir?
his own life and destiny?
¿Su propia vida y destino?
Then I put myself in his shoes,
Entonces me puse en su lugar,
and thought about it.
y lo pensé.
If I were him,
Si yo fuera él,
would I have done any better?
¿Lo habría hecho mejor?
Maybe I would've made the same choice.
Quizás yo habría tomado la misma decisión.
"He"?
"Él"?
Who is "he"?
Quién es él"?
A family member.
Un miembro de la familia.
Family?
¿Familia?
I don't know how to comfort you,
No sé cómo consolarte,
or help your family.
o ayuda a tu familia.
But I do know,
Pero sí lo sé,
if it were me,
Si fuera yo,
I would stay by her side.
Me quedaría a su lado.
Even if I couldn't do anything.
Aunque no pudiera hacer nada.
Thank you for telling me that.
Gracias por decírmelo.
I'll get going then.
Me pondré en marcha entonces.
(Outpatient Building)
(Edificio de pacientes ambulatorios)
- Grandma. - Xiao Ye.
Abuela. Xiao Ye.
You're here.
Estás aquí.
- How are you recovering? - Did you get wet?
- ¿Cómo te estás recuperando? - ¿Te mojaste?
No, I'm fine.
No, estoy bien.
How are you feeling?
¿Cómo te sientes?
Good.
Bien.
Wu Zi has been here taking care of me every day.
Wu Zi ha estado aquí cuidándome todos los días.
I'm recovering very well.
Me estoy recuperando muy bien.
That's good.
Eso es bueno.
I brought you some fish soup.
Te traje un poco de sopa de pescado.
Drink plenty of it later.
Bebe mucho después.
It'll help you get some calcium and recover faster.
Te ayudará a obtener calcio y a recuperarte más rápido.
Okay.
Bueno.
Okay, that's enough. Good.
Vale, ya es suficiente. Bien.
Here.
Aquí.
- Okay. - Here.
- De acuerdo. - Aquí.
Piping hot fish soup.
Sopa de pescado bien caliente.
- Here, have a taste. - Okay.
- Toma, prueba. - De acuerdo.
How is it?
¿Cómo está?
It's delicious.
Está delicioso.
Ian Fang made this soup, didn't she?
Ian Fang preparó esta sopa, ¿verdad?
How did you know?
¿Cómo lo supiste?
I've been eating her cooking for decades.
Llevo décadas comiendo su comida.
How could I not know?
¿Cómo iba a no saberlo?
Look.
Mirar.
When she makes fish soup,
Cuando ella prepara sopa de pescado,
there won't be a single bone in it.
No tendrá ni un solo hueso.
Grandma.
Abuela.
Auntie asked me to tell you
La tía me pidió que te lo dijera.
that once she's settled things with He Xiao Lian,
que una vez que haya arreglado las cosas con He Xiao Lian,
she'll come to see you.
Ella vendrá a verte.
Good.
Bien.
Drink it while it's hot.
Bébelo mientras esté caliente.
(Outpatient Building)
(Edificio de pacientes ambulatorios)
(Teachers' Office)
(Oficina de Profesores)
Come in.
Adelante.
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
Xing Wu's mom, what brings you here?
Mamá de Xing Wu, ¿qué te trae por aquí?
I
I
I'm here to bring you some soup.
Vengo a traerte un poco de sopa.
Look at you, it's already noon.
Mírate, ya es mediodía.
Why are you still eating instant noodles?
¿Por qué sigues comiendo fideos instantáneos?
You teach and shape your students.
Tú enseñas y formas a tus alumnos.
Have some soup to nourish yourself.
Toma un poco de sopa para nutrirte.
It smells delicious.
Huele delicioso.
Go ahead and drink it.
Adelante, bébelo.
You're here for a reason, right?
Estás aquí por alguna razón, ¿verdad?
Yes, I need your help with something.
Sí, necesito tu ayuda con algo.
I can probably guess what it is.
Probablemente puedo adivinar qué es.
Well...
Bien...
Xiao Lian has been avoiding me.
Xiao Lian me ha estado evitando.
But I really need to see her.
Pero realmente necesito verla.
So I was hoping you could help me...
Así que esperaba que pudieras ayudarme...
No problem.
Ningún problema.
After all, He Xiao Lian and I
Después de todo, He Xiao Lian y yo
were together for many years.
Estuvieron juntos durante muchos años.
I know her temperament and personality best.
Conozco mejor que nadie su temperamento y su personalidad.
How about this? I'll go with you to see her.
¿Qué te parece esto? Iré contigo a verla.
You'll come with me?
¿Vendrás conmigo?
- It's fine. - Thank you, Mr. Zhu.
- Está bien. - Gracias, señor Zhu.
- Thank you. - Don't mention it.
- Gracias. - De nada.
Just think of it as doing it for Xing Wu.
Piensa que lo estás haciendo por Xing Wu.
Xiao Lian, you're at home.
Xiao Lian, estás en casa.
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
- Xiao Lian. Xiao Lian! - Xiao... Xiao Lian!
-Xiao Lian. ¡Xiao Lian! - Xiao... ¡Xiao Lian!
- Xiao Lian. - Let go!
- Xiao Lian. - ¡Suéltame!
- We need to talk to you.
- Necesitamos hablar contigo.
This is Li Ian Fang, the mother of my student, Xing Wu.
Ella es Li Ian Fang, la madre de mi alumno, Xing Wu.
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
Well, I'm here to bring you the money today.
Bueno, hoy estoy aquí para traerte el dinero.
It's so thin. This isn't 30,000, is it?
Es tan delgada. Esto no son 30.000, ¿verdad?
It's true, it's not 30,000.
Es cierto, no son 30.000.
Your medical bill was 1,500.
Su factura médica fue de 1.500.
As for the rest,
En cuanto al resto,
you can buy whatever you'd like with it.
Puedes comprar lo que quieras con él.
We agreed on 30,000, so 30,000 it is.
Acordamos 30.000, así que serán 30.000.
Xiao Lian.
Xiaolian.
I had to scrape this money together.
Tuve que reunir este dinero a duras penas.
Xuandao is closed while we sort things out,
Xuandao está cerrado mientras resolvemos las cosas.
and my mom is in the hospital too.
Y mi madre también está en el hospital.
That takes money too.
Eso también cuesta dinero.
Our family is really struggling now.
Nuestra familia está pasando por momentos muy difíciles.
We really can't come up with 30,000 yuan.
Realmente no podemos reunir 30.000 yuanes.
Look, it's not easy for anyone.
Mira, no es fácil para nadie.
Besides,
Además,
your allergy looks almost healed.
Tu alergia parece casi curada.
Your tattooed eyebrows look great.
Tus cejas tatuadas se ven geniales.
- You'll be fine in a few days. - None of your business!
- Estarás bien en unos días. - ¡No es asunto tuyo!
Li Ian Fang,
Li Ian Fang,
since you can't pay the 30,000,
ya que no puedes pagar los 30.000,
there's nothing more to say.
No hay nada más que decir.
- Just leave. - Xiao Lian.
- Simplemente vete. - Xiao Lian.
I'm begging you.
Te lo ruego.
Please, just take this money first.
Por favor, tome este dinero primero.
Stop wasting your time!
¡Deja de perder el tiempo!
- Go! - I'll do anything you want!
¡Vete! ¡Haré lo que quieras!
I'll kneel to you.
Me arrodillaré ante ti.
- You... - I... Xiao Lian. I'm so sorry.
- Tú... - Yo... Xiao Lian. Lo siento mucho.
Li Ian Fang, come on. Get up, get up.
Li Ian Fang, vamos. Levántate, levántate.
He Xiao Lian!
¡Él Xiao Lian!
What are you doing?
¿Qué estás haciendo?
Zhu Feng!
¡Zhu Feng!
That's enough already.
Ya basta.
Fine.
Bien.
Let's leave it at that.
Dejémoslo así.
Come on, it's okay now.
Vamos, ya está bien.
Come.
Venir.
- Is it settled then? - It's settled.
- ¿Está resuelto entonces? - Está resuelto.
Here, Xing Wu's mom.
Aquí está la madre de Xing Wu.
- Mr. Zhu. - It's so hot today.
—Señor Zhu. —Hace muchísimo calor hoy.
- Here, have some milk tea. - Thank you.
- Toma, aquí tienes un té con leche. - Gracias.
My students love this stuff.
A mis alumnos les encanta esto.
It's good.
Está bien.
Mr. Zhu.
Sr. Zhu
I
I
I want to thank you.
Quiero darte las gracias.
You... You mean what happened just now?
¿Te refieres a lo que acaba de pasar?
I could've just been the one to kneel.
Podría haber sido yo quien se arrodillara.
But you came along and got scolded too.
Pero tú también llegaste y te regañaron.
You... Isn't it fine as long as it's settled?
Tú... ¿No está bien siempre y cuando esté resuelto?
I don't mind.
No me importa.
You don't know this. But in front of He Xiao Lian,
No lo sabes. Pero frente a He Xiao Lian,
I'm... used to it.
Estoy... acostumbrado.
Xiao Lian
xiao lian
she isn't a bad person.
Ella no es mala persona.
She's just too hot-tempered.
Es que tiene muy mal genio.
As for me, I'm too mild.
En cuanto a mí, soy demasiado suave.
She always says to me, "Zhu Feng,"
Ella siempre me dice: "Zhu Feng",
"you're a grown man."
"Eres un hombre adulto."
"Why are you always so submissive?"
"¿Por qué eres siempre tan sumisa?"
"A man should have some backbone."
"Un hombre debería tener carácter."
"Don't you know that?"
"¿No lo sabes?"
How could I not know that?
¿Cómo iba a ignorar eso?
I just feel that
Simplemente siento que
a home isn't a place
un hogar no es un lugar
where reason matters most.
donde la razón es lo que más importa.
Facing reality,
Enfrentando la realidad,
I can be flexible.
Puedo ser flexible.
But my dreams have nowhere to go.
Pero mis sueños no tienen adónde ir.
Admitting my mistakes isn't about compromise.
Admitir mis errores no implica ceder.
It's the wisdom of using softness to overcome hardness.
Se trata de la sabiduría de usar la suavidad para vencer la dureza.
It's just that...
Es que...
He Xiao Lian is too hard.
He Xiao Lian es demasiado difícil.
I've never managed to overcome her.
Nunca he logrado superarla.
Mr. Zhu,
Sr. Zhu,
whatever comes out of your mouth
lo que salga de tu boca
always sounds very reasonable.
Siempre suena muy razonable.
Well, I am a teacher, after all.
Bueno, al fin y al cabo soy profesor.
Actually, Xing Wu's mom,
En realidad, la madre de Xing Wu,
I quite admire you.
Te admiro mucho.
Admire me?
¿Me admiras?
I've made such a mess of my life.
He hecho un desastre con mi vida.
What is there to admire?
¿Qué hay que admirar?
Have you heard of trigonometric functions?
¿Has oído hablar de las funciones trigonométricas?
What?
¿Qué?
Trigonometric functions.
Funciones trigonométricas.
Their periodic fluctuations
Sus fluctuaciones periódicas
follow a predictable pattern.
siguen un patrón predecible.
The highs and lows alternate.
Los altibajos se alternan.
It's a bit like our lives.
Es un poco como nuestras vidas.
Look, you might be
Mira, podrías ser
at a low point in your life right now.
En un momento difícil de tu vida ahora mismo.
But I believe
Pero yo creo
that as long as you
eso mientras tú
live your life positively,
vive tu vida positivamente,
sooner or later, you'll trace out
Tarde o temprano, lo descubrirás.
a perfect curve.
una curva perfecta.
One that shows an upward trend.
Una que muestre una tendencia al alza.
Mr. Zhu, I understand.
Señor Zhu, lo entiendo.
You mean to say my luck is about to change?
¿Quieres decir que mi suerte está a punto de cambiar?
Something like that.
Algo así.
From your lips to God's ears!
¡Que Dios te bendiga!
Well...
Bien...
May the Sea Goddess bless me.
Que la Diosa del Mar me bendiga.
Bless me, Li Ian Fang.
Bendíceme, Li Ian Fang.
Let my luck change soon!
¡Ojalá mi suerte cambie pronto!
Mr. Zhu, when you come to Xuandao,
Señor Zhu, cuando venga a Xuandao,
I'll give you a free haircut.
Te haré un corte de pelo gratis.
That wouldn't be right. Things aren't easy for you either.
Eso no sería correcto. Las cosas tampoco son fáciles para ti.
If you really want to thank me,
Si de verdad quieres darme las gracias,
then do this.
entonces haz esto.
Have Xing Wu come thank me at school.
Que Xing Wu venga a darme las gracias en la escuela.
Actually, the way Wu Zi is now...
En realidad, la forma en que Wu Zi está ahora...
It's all my fault as his mother.
Todo es culpa mía como su madre.
Don't say that.
No digas eso.
Xing Wu is a good kid.
Xing Wu es un buen chico.
I just think it's a shame for him to quit school.
Me parece una pena que haya dejado los estudios.
The children's future shouldn't be ruined
El futuro de los niños no debe arruinarse.
by the difficulties we adults face.
por las dificultades a las que nos enfrentamos los adultos.
Don't you agree?
¿No estás de acuerdo?
Yes.
Sí.
Well, since I'm helping you out,
Bueno, ya que te estoy ayudando,
how about I give you a ride back?
¿Qué te parece si te llevo de vuelta?
Sure.
Seguro.
- Watch your step. - Okay.
- Cuidado al caminar. - De acuerdo.
Xing Wu's mom,
La madre de Xing Wu,
this next song is dedicated to you!
¡Esta próxima canción está dedicada a ti!
Great!
¡Excelente!
I'm home.
Estoy en casa.
You're back.
Has vuelto.
I heard from Zhu Feng
He oído hablar de Zhu Feng
that you settled the compensation issue.
que usted resolvió el problema de la compensación.
He told you?
¿Te lo dijo?
Why would he tell you
¿Por qué te lo diría?
about all my embarrassing secrets?
¿Sobre todos mis secretos vergonzosos?
Embarrassing secrets?
¿Secretos vergonzosos?
What did he tell you?
¿Qué te dijo?
He said
Él dijo
you're a steel rose.
Eres una rosa de acero.
"Turning the tide when all is lost..."
"Cambiar el rumbo cuando todo está perdido..."
"And holding it all together when it's falling apart."
"Y mantenerlo todo unido cuando se está desmoronando."
I only understood the first part.
Solo entendí la primera parte.
Well,
Bien,
the rest is true as well.
El resto también es cierto.
By the way, is Grandma getting discharged
Por cierto, ¿ le dan el alta a la abuela?
this weekend?
¿Este fin de semana?
The doctor said she's recovering well.
El médico dijo que se está recuperando bien.
She can come home to recuperate this weekend.
Podrá volver a casa este fin de semana para recuperarse.
That's great.
Genial.
I've been busy these past few days
He estado ocupado estos últimos días.
sorting out the licensing paperwork.
Tramitando la documentación para la obtención de la licencia.
I'll get her room ready in a bit.
En un rato le prepararé la habitación.
I'll do it.
Lo haré.
Also, I ordered
Además, hice un pedido
a new roll-up banner.
un nuevo banner enrollable.
Aren't we reopening soon?
¿No vamos a reabrir pronto?
When you're free, help me go pick it up.
Cuando tengas tiempo libre, ayúdame a ir a recogerlo.
Sure.
Seguro.
(Zhazhating)
(Zhazhating)
They're here.
Están aquí.
She's back, she's back.
Ha vuelto, ha vuelto.
Wu Zi.
Wu Zi.
Mom.
Mamá.
Careful, careful.
Cuidado, cuidado.
Careful, Mom. Don't rush.
Cuidado, mamá. No te apresures.
I'm back.
Ya estoy de vuelta.
- Slowly.
-Despacio.
- Thank you, sir. - Careful.
- Gracias, señor. - Cuidado.
Xiao Ye.
Xiao Ye.
- Okay, thank you. - We're home.
- Vale, gracias. - Ya estamos en casa.
- Mom, Mom. - Ian Fang.
- Mamá, mamá. - Ian Fang.
Mom, how are you feeling?
Mamá, ¿cómo te sientes?
- Are you okay? - Good.
- ¿Estás bien? - Bien.
Let me tell you,
Déjame decirte,
everything is sorted out now.
Ya está todo solucionado.
The business license is ready too.
La licencia comercial también está lista.
Look, we even put up
Mira, incluso pusimos
a grand reopening sign.
un cartel de gran reapertura.
That's wonderful.
Eso es maravilloso.
You won't make that mistake again, right?
No volverás a cometer ese error, ¿verdad?
I won't, I won't. Never again.
No lo haré, no lo haré. Nunca más.
Then, let's take a photo.
Entonces, tomemos una foto.
- Sure, to celebrate the occasion. - Let's do it.
- Claro, para celebrar la ocasión. - Hagámoslo.
- Okay. - Grandma.
- De acuerdo. - Abuela.
- Come on. - Everyone, get ready.
—Vamos. —Todos, prepárense.
I'll count down from three!
¡Contaré hacia atrás desde tres!
- Okay.
- De acuerdo.
Three, two, one.
Tres, dos, uno.
Cheese!
¡Queso!
One more.
Una vez más.
Three, two, one.
Tres, dos, uno.
Cheese!
¡Queso!
Help me check. Is it straight?
Ayúdame a comprobarlo. ¿Está recto?
- It's crooked. - No, it's crooked.
- Está torcido. - No, está torcido.
- No. To the right. - How about now? Is it straight?
- No. A la derecha. - ¿Y ahora? ¿Está recto?
- To the right a little. - It's still crooked, son.
- Un poco a la derecha. - Todavía está torcido, hijo.
Is it straight?
¿Es recto?
It's just right now.
Es justo ahora.
- That's it. - Okay.
- Eso es todo. - De acuerdo.
It's good?
¿Está bien?
I'll listen to Grandma.
Voy a escuchar a la abuela.
Looking at this photo really warms my heart.
Ver esta foto me llena el corazón de alegría.
Our Xuandao will surely get better and better.
Nuestro Xuandao seguramente irá mejorando cada vez más.
Harmony in the family brings prosperity.
La armonía en la familia trae prosperidad.
Exactly. Auntie,
Exactamente. Tía,
with your optimistic attitude,
con tu actitud optimista,
you'll succeed in anything.
Tendrás éxito en cualquier cosa.
Ms. Fang, I believe
Señora Fang, creo
you'll lead Xuandao
Tú liderarás Xuandao
to grow bigger and stronger.
para crecer más grande y más fuerte.
- Good. - Bigger and stronger!
- Bien. - ¡Más grande y más fuerte!
Yes, bigger and stronger!
¡Sí, más grande y más fuerte!
Good, good.
Bien, bien.
(Xuandao Show Hair Salon)
(Salón de belleza Xuandao Show)
Here.
Aquí.
The weather changed so fast.
El tiempo cambió muy rápido.
It was clear and sunny just now.
Hace un momento estaba despejado y soleado.
Suddenly, it's raining.
De repente, empieza a llover.
That's life, I guess.
Así es la vida, supongo.
One second,
Un segundo,
it's clear and sunny.
Está despejado y soleado.
The next, it's a storm.
Lo siguiente que viene es una tormenta.
So, Boss Xing,
Entonces, Jefe Xing,
when are you planning to start your job in the county?
¿Cuándo tienes previsto empezar a trabajar en el condado?
I haven't decided yet.
Todavía no me he decidido.
Did you delay it because of Grandma's situation?
¿Lo retrasaste por la situación de la abuela?
No.
No.
What?
¿Qué?
Do you want to persuade me to go back to school again?
¿Quieres convencerme para que vuelva a estudiar?
If taking that job in the county
Si acepta ese trabajo en el condado
is the best choice you can make
es la mejor opción que puedes tomar
at this moment,
en este momento,
I won't oppose it anymore.
Ya no me opondré.
No more pushing me to study?
¿Ya no me presionan para que estudie?
No more.
No más.
Why?
¿Por qué?
Because I believe in you.
Porque creo en ti.
No matter which path you take,
No importa qué camino tomes,
even if it's stormy along the way,
incluso si hay tormenta en el camino,
you will reach your own Rome.
Llegarás a tu propia Roma.
And I promise,
Y te lo prometo,
no matter what you decide,
No importa lo que decidas,
I will firmly support you.
Te apoyaré firmemente.
I got it.
Lo tengo.
How could she be like this?
¿Cómo podía ser así?
- This is mind-blowing. - Look.
- Esto es alucinante. - Mira.
I thought her family was poor.
Pensaba que su familia era pobre.
Turns out she's a rich kid.
Resulta que es una niña rica.
Yet she had the nerve to take the living allowance.
Sin embargo, tuvo el descaro de aceptar el subsidio de manutención.
Her family has a criminal record.
Su familia tiene antecedentes penales.
Then she can't become a civil servant, right?
Entonces no puede convertirse en funcionaria pública, ¿verdad?
Her dad's money is suspicious.
El dinero de su padre resulta sospechoso.
How could she be any good herself?
¿Cómo podría ella ser buena?
Look, it's her.
Mira, es ella.
It's her.
Es ella.
Qing Ye.
Qingye.
This is bad. Something happened.
Esto es malo. Algo ha pasado.
- What's wrong? - Did you see the post
- ¿Qué pasa? - ¿Viste la publicación?
on the campus forum?
¿En el foro del campus?
What post?
¿Qué publicación?
(She thought she could hide here and that no one would find out...)
(Pensaba que podía esconderse aquí y que nadie se enteraría...)
(about the dirty secrets in her family.)
(Sobre los sucios secretos de su familia.)
(Such a poser. Always stealing the spotlight.)
(¡Qué pretencioso! Siempre robando el protagonismo.)
(Shouldn't the school take this more seriously?)
(¿No debería la escuela tomarse esto más en serio?)
Stop it. The more you comb it,
Basta. Cuanto más lo peines,
the more it looks like a dog chewed it.
Cuanto más parezca que lo ha mordisqueado un perro.
It actually was chewed by a dog.
En realidad, fue mordisqueado por un perro.
Where did you get it cut? I really need to avoid that place.
¿Dónde te lo cortaste? De verdad necesito evitar ese lugar.
Want some? My family dried them.
¿Quieres probarlos? Mi familia los secó.
Aren't you afraid of me?
¿No me tienes miedo?
No.
No.
Those people just believe whatever rumors they hear.
Esa gente se cree cualquier rumor que oye.
Not me.
Yo no.
Shi Min.
Shi Min.
Qing Ye, come here!
¡Qing Ye, ven aquí!
I saved you a seat. Hurry.
Te he guardado un asiento. Date prisa.
Chicken leg.
Muslo de pollo.
- What are you doing? - Are you blind?
- ¿Qué estás haciendo? - ¿Estás ciego?
Why did you bump into her on purpose?
¿Por qué chocaste con ella a propósito?
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
Are you okay?
¿Estás bien?
I didn't do it on purpose either.
Yo tampoco lo hice a propósito.
- It was an accident. - Are you crazy?
- Fue un accidente. - ¿Estás loco?
You did that on purpose.
Lo hiciste a propósito.
Well, we didn't do it on purpose.
Bueno, no lo hicimos a propósito.
Qing Ye, you're the one who dirtied Li Wen Hui's clothes!
¡Qing Ye, tú fuiste quien ensució la ropa de Li Wen Hui!
Everyone saw it clearly!
¡Todos lo vieron claramente!
Don't you all agree?
¿No están todos de acuerdo?
- Yes! - Yes, my foot!
- ¡Sí! - ¡Sí, mi pie!
Forget it, Fang Lei. She's protected by thugs.
Olvídalo, Fang Lei. Está protegida por matones.
We can't afford to mess with her.
No podemos permitirnos meternos con ella.
If you've got a problem, come at me.
Si tienes algún problema, ven a hablar conmigo.
There's no need to drag others into it!
¡No hay necesidad de involucrar a otros!
Then what about you bullying...
¿Y qué hay del acoso escolar?
Fang Lei and the others?
¿Fang Lei y los demás?
What do you have to say for yourself?
¿Qué tienes que decir en tu defensa?
Me? Bullying them?
¿Yo? ¿Acosándolos?
Zhu... Zhu... Zhu.
Zhu... Zhu... Zhu.
- Mr. Zhu! - What's wrong?
- ¡Señor Zhu! - ¿Qué ocurre?
Qing Ye got into a fight
Qing Ye se metió en una pelea
in the cafeteria.
en la cafetería.
You chopped off both their hair.
Les cortaste el pelo a los dos.
You even threatened them not to tell anyone.
Incluso los amenazaste para que no se lo contaran a nadie.
Isn't that bullying?
¿Eso no es acoso escolar?
Fang Lei, am I telling the truth?
Fang Lei, ¿estoy diciendo la verdad?
- I... - Of course it is!
- Yo... - ¡Por supuesto que sí!
Look at Fang Lei's hair. It's completely ruined.
Mira el pelo de Fang Lei. Está completamente arruinado.
You guys were the ones who started it.
Ustedes fueron quienes lo iniciaron.
I was being bullied. Am I not allowed to fight back?
Estaba sufriendo acoso. ¿Acaso no tengo derecho a defenderme?
You scratched her hand, didn't you?
Le arañaste la mano, ¿verdad?
Isn't that bullying?
¿Eso no es acoso escolar?
It was self-defense. Believe it or not.
Fue en defensa propia. Aunque parezca increíble.
Stop right there!
¡Alto ahí!
Fang Lei and Li Wen Hui just want an apology.
Fang Lei y Li Wen Hui solo quieren una disculpa.
Is that too much to ask?
¿Es mucho pedir?
Just because you're from the big city,
Solo porque eres de la gran ciudad,
you think you can twist the truth.
Crees que puedes distorsionar la verdad.
We just want an apology.
Solo queremos una disculpa.
Apologize! Apologize! Apologize!
¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate!
- Shut up! - You'd better apologize!
¡Cállate! ¡Será mejor que te disculpes!
Shut up!
¡Callarse la boca!
Shut your mouth!
¡Cierra el pico!
Apologize! Apologize! Apologize!
¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate!
- Apologize! Apologize! Apologize! - Shut up!
- ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! - ¡Cállate!
Apologize! Apologize! Apologize!
¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate!
Shut up!
¡Callarse la boca!
- Come with me. - Apologize!
- Ven conmigo. - ¡Discúlpate!
Apologize! Apologize! Apologize!
¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate! ¡Discúlpate!
Qing Ye, what's going on?
Qing Ye, ¿qué está pasando?
Xing Wu! Where are you going?
¡Xing Wu! ¿Adónde vas?
You're such a bully!
¡Eres un matón!
Bully!
¡Matón!
The teacher is here!
¡El profesor está aquí!
How can you be such a bully?
¿Cómo puedes ser tan acosador?
You're bullying her!
¡La estás acosando!
What are you all doing?
¿Qué estáis haciendo todos?
This is the cafeteria. It's a place to eat.
Esta es la cafetería. Es un lugar para comer.
Let me remind you all.
Permítanme recordárselo a todos.
Every one of you here
Todos ustedes aquí
will only be a high school student once in your life.
Solo serás estudiante de secundaria una vez en tu vida.
Don't do anything you'll look back on and regret
No hagas nada de lo que luego te arrepientas.
years after graduation.
años después de la graduación.
I'll hold onto this.
Me quedaré con esto.
You must be hungry.
Debes tener hambre.
Try some.
Prueba algunos.
What is this?
¿Qué es esto?
Agar jelly.
Gelatina, gelatina.
It's a local specialty.
Es una especialidad local.
Go ahead and eat. It's not poisoned.
Puedes comerlo sin problema. No está envenenado.
It's savory.
Es sabroso.
It's good, right?
Está bien, ¿verdad?
Didn't you go with Shu Han
¿No fuiste con Shu Han?
to see Mr. Ye?
¿Para ver al Sr. Ye?
Why are you here?
¿Por qué estás aquí?
What a coincidence, right?
¡Qué coincidencia, ¿verdad?!
I was just passing by.
Solo estaba de paso.
Mr. Wu, emergency!
Señor Wu, ¡emergencia!
Qing Ye is in trouble.
Qing Ye está en problemas.
Qing Ye, you're the one
Qing Ye, tú eres la única
who dirtied Li Wen Hui's clothes!
¡Quién ensució la ropa de Li Wen Hui!
I have to go.
Tengo que irme.
Something urgent came up.
Surgió algo urgente.
What about Mr. Ye?
¿Y qué hay del señor Ye?
You know how rare this opportunity is.
Sabes lo excepcional que es esta oportunidad.
Apologize to him for me.
Discúlpate con él de mi parte.
I'll make it up to him next time.
La próxima vez me compensaré.
Xing Wu!
¡Xing Wu!
I originally thought
Originalmente pensé
that once I got to Zhazhating,
que una vez que llegué a Zhazhating,
everything would come to an end.
Todo llegaría a su fin.
I thought I could start over.
Pensé que podría empezar de nuevo.
This is a small town.
Este es un pueblo pequeño.
Even the smallest thing
Incluso la cosa más pequeña
will spread like wildfire.
se extenderá como la pólvora.
Everyone's life is boring,
La vida de todos es aburrida,
so they like to be spectators.
Así que les gusta ser espectadores.
They love a good story.
Les encantan las buenas historias.
So they'll add their own spin,
Así que le darán su propio toque,
make things up,
inventar cosas,
and pass off fiction as fact.
y hacer pasar la ficción por realidad.
The more bizarre, the better.
Cuanto más extraño, mejor.
Exactly.
Exactamente.
They don't care about the truth.
No les importa la verdad.
But they also have short memories.
Pero también tienen poca memoria.
In a few days, when new gossip arrives,
En unos días, cuando lleguen nuevos chismes,
the old stories are completely forgotten.
Las viejas historias han caído completamente en el olvido.
Don't take it to heart.
No te lo tomes a pecho.
The rumor-mongers might forget,
Los que difunden rumores podrían olvidarlo,
but what about the victims?
¿Pero qué pasa con las víctimas?
What about the pain they've suffered?
¿Y qué hay del dolor que han sufrido?
What are you doing?
¿Qué estás haciendo?
Close your eyes.
Cierra los ojos.
Take a deep breath.
Respira hondo.